Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is צ"ד Tzadi Daled
מנחות Menachos 94. We pick up at the bottom of צ"ג Tzadi
Gimmel עמוד ב', Amud Beis, the משנה, Mishnah, three lines from the
bottom. We are finishing one פרק Perek and beginning the next one
today. The פרק Perek we're finishing, שתי מידות, Shtei Middos, started out
with a discussion about measurements, dry and liquid measurements in the בית
המקדש, Base Hamikdash, but then moved on to be making some broader
and general statements about what types of animals you bring נסכים Nesachim
for, what types of animals you do סמיכה Smicha for, and now
we're in the middle of some really general ways of categorizing and
talking about the קרבנות Korbanos as a whole and really much more
animal קרבנות, Korbanos, not מנחות, Menachos, but for some reason it's in
this מסכת. Masechet. And now we're going to wrap up the discussion
of סמיכה Smicha by a comparison, contrast and comparison to תנופה, Tenufa,
the waving that you sometimes do with certain קרבנות. Korbanos. So let's
take a look. חומר בסמיכה מבתנופה ובתנופה מבסמיכה. Chomer b'smicha m'bitnufa u'vitnufa
m'bismicha. There are ways that סמיכה Smicha is weightier than תנופה Tenufa
and ways that תנופה, Tenufa, the waving, is weightier than the סמיכה.
Smicha. שהיחיד מניף לכל חבריו ואין אחד סומך לכל חבריו. Shehayachid manif
l'chol chaverav v'ein echad somech l'chol chaverav. Okay, so this is the
way in which the סמיכה Smicha is weightier because when it comes
to תנופה, Tenufa, one person only, if you have a group, if
you have שותפים Shutafim that are bringing a קרבן, Korban, a group
of people that are bringing a קרבן, Korban, only one person does
the תנופה. Tenufa. You don't have everybody doing the תנופה. Tenufa. The
גמרא Gemara is going to explain why is because you're only allowed
to do one תנופה Tenufa and you can't get everybody's hand on
it and your hand has to be directly on the object that
you're doing the that you're doing the תנופה Tenufa on. So it's
just not physically possible. So only one of them does it on
behalf of everybody whereas סמיכה Smicha you do not have one person
do סמיכה Smicha on behalf of everybody; everybody does their סמיכה. Smicha.
They can do it sequentially and everybody does a סמיכה Smicha as
we sort of said, סמיכה Smicha is about a sort of a
way of emphasizing ownership and connection, so it makes sense that you
would want each person to do that. Whereas תנופה Tenufa is a
ritual that you do but maybe somebody can represent the group in
terms of doing תנופה. Tenufa. So this is seen as a way
that סמיכה Smicha is weightier because סמיכה Smicha makes a bigger demand,
as it were, that every individual must do it. You're not allowed
to have one person. So סמיכה Smicha is weightier in that way.
חומר בתנופה, Chomer bitnufa, תנופה, Tenufa, and here's the way in which
תנופה Tenufa is weightier: שתנופה נוהגת בקרבנות היחיד ובקרבנות הציבור. Shetnufa noheget
b'korbanos hayachid u'v'korbanos hatzibbur. תנופה Tenufa has a much broader application. You
do it by individual קרבנות, Korbanos, you do it by, you know,
when you bring a שלמים, Shlamim, private קרבן, Korban, you bring a
שלמים, Shlamim, you wave the breast and the side. ובקרבנות הציבור, U'v'korbanos
hatzibbur,
and in communal קרבנות, Korbanos, we've been discussing that, that's the שתי,
that's the זבחי שלמי ציבור by the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem.
So you do it by both of those. בחיים ובשחוטים, Bechayim u'vishchutim,
you do it both when the animal is alive, that's what you
do by the lambs by שבועות, Shavuos, and בשחוטים Bishchutim by the
thigh and the breast of all of שלמים Shlamim by the after
the animal has been shechted. ובדבר שיש בו רוח חיים ובדבר שאין
בו רוח חיים. U'v'davar sheyesh bo ruach chayim u'v'davar she'ein bo ruach
chayim. Something that is alive and even something that's not alive you'll
do תנופה Tenufa with sometimes with, you know, the breads, so of
that you bring with the lambs and the bread of the תודה
Toda and also with, as רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi says כל
לחמי תודה ונסכים, Kol lachmei toda u'nesachim, also the נסכים Nesachim that
come with the קרבן. Korban. So all of those things that even
אין בו רוח חיים. Ein bo ruach chayim. מה שאין כן בסמיכה,
Mah she'ein kein bismicha, which is not so by סמיכה. Smicha. סמיכה
Smicha is only done on an animal and only when the animal
is alive. Okay, so let's take a look at now how the
גמרא Gemara explains this. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, top of צ"ד Tzadi
Daled עמוד א'. Amud Aleph. Our rabbis taught: קרבנו Korbano לרבות כל
בעלי קרבן לסמיכה. le'rabos kol ba'alei korban le'smicha. So we saw this
yesterday, his קרבן, Korban, you know again, this emphasis of ownership, and
everybody, it has to be every individual's קרבן, Korban, so every individual
וסמך ידו על ראש קרבנו, vesamach yado al rosh korbano, his hand,
his קרבן, Korban, every individual has to do it. שיכול ולא דין
הוא, Sheyachol v'lo din hu,
that I could have said the opposite, I could have made a
קל וחומר Kal v'Chomer to say not that way. Why? ומה תנופה
שנתרבתה בשחוטים, U'mah tenufa shenitrabsa b'shchutim, תנופה Tenufa is weightier as we've
seen, it applies to a much broader
category of things and it applies to שחוטים, shchutim, that's only one
of the ways in which it's broader, but it applies to a
much broader category of things. נתמעטה בחברים Nismata b'chovrim and nevertheless when
it comes to a חבורה, Chabura, a group, it's shrunk, okay? It
does not, you don't have the whole group doing it. It only
has one person of the group doing it.
סמיכה שלא נתרבתה בשחוטים, Smicha shelo nitrabsa b'shchutim, סמיכה Smicha that is
not as weighty, that it's, you know, that it's only a small
that you only do it on an animal. smaller number of items,
אינו דין שתסמך בכל פן? einu din she-tismach b'chol pen? How much
more so should I say that, you know, it should have a
smaller number of people that do it? You don't have everybody doing
סמיכה. Smicha. So, it's a little funny, like, do you feel the
idea that everybody is doing סמיכה Smicha is a weighty thing or
is it a nice thing that everybody gets the opportunity to do
סמיכה? Smicha? But the גמרא Gemara here, you know, the way the
משנה Mishna framed it, it's like a weighty thing. It's a demand.
So, if תנופה—so Tnufa if סמיכה Smicha is narrower and it only
applies to a smaller group of things, it makes sense that the
demands should also be less. And it's a קל וחומר, Kal V'chomer,
if even by תנופה Tnufa the demand is only one person should
do it for everyone, certainly by סמיכה Smicha the demand should not
be any greater than that, and one person would do it for
everyone. תלמוד לומר קרבנו, Talmud lomar korbano, that's why you needed the
פסוק. Pasuk. His קרבן, Korban, every individual who is part of this
קרבן Korban has to be do סמיכה. Smicha. לרבות כל בעלי קרבן
לסמיכה. L'rabot kol ba'alei korban l'smicha. Okay, so that's how we know
that principle. Everybody, every individual, even if it's a joint קרבן, Korban,
has to do סמיכה. Smicha. So now the גמרא—the Gemara ברייתא Braita
goes in the reverse. ותסרב תנופה בחוברין מקל וחומר. V'tisarev tnufa b'chovrin
mi-kal v'chomer. So now that we've established that, that סמיכה Smicha is
each individual, now let's go ahead and say that, you know, that
the same will be true by תנופה, Tnufa, that תנופה Tnufa will
be expanded by חוברין, Chovrin, the חבורה, Chabura, the people who do
it. Okay, what's going to be the קל וחומר? Kal V'chomer? ומה
סמיכה מקל וחומר,
ומה סמיכה שלא נתרבתה בשחוטין, U'ma smicha mi-kal v'chomer, u'ma smicha she-lo
nitravta b'shechutin, סמיכה Smicha is narrower, it doesn't apply to animals that
are שחוטים, Shechutim, it's a smaller scope, נתרבתה בחוברין, nitravta b'chovrin, but
it's broader, it, you know, makes more of demands in that every
individual does the
סמיכה. Smicha. תנופה שנתרבתה בשחוטין, Tnufa she-nitravta b'shechutin, תנופה Tnufa that's a
broader scope and weightier and that it applies even to שחוטי Shechuti
animals, אינו דין שנתרבתה בחוברין? einu din she-nitravta b'chovrin? How much more
so should it be broader and weightier and have every person who's
part of the קרבן Korban do תנופה? Tnufa? So why not? Which
is another way of saying what's the basis of saying that you
don't have everybody do תנופה? Tnufa? משום דלא אפשר, Mishum d'lo efshar,
and interestingly it's not a פסוק, Pasuk, it's just logically not possible.
Okay, why not? היכי לעביד? Heichi l'avid? What, how do you want
to do it? לינפו כולהו בהדי הדדי? Leinpu kulhu bahadi hadadi? Have
everybody do תנופה Tnufa at the same time? הוי חציצה. Havi chatzitza.
Then there's, you know, all the hands won't fit on the object
you're doing תנופה Tnufa on. So somebody's hand is going to be
in the way of somebody else's hand, and it won't be directly
in contact with the—with, you know, the חזה ושוק Chazeh v'shok or
whatever it is you're doing תנופה, Tnufa, and that's understood to be
not acceptable. So לינפוס דהדי ולינפוס, leinfus dahadi v'leinfus, to let each
person do it sequentially like we would do by the
סמיכה? Smicha? No. תנופה רחמנא ולא תנופות. Tnufa Rachmana v'lo tnufot. It
says a תנופה, Tnufa, you know, you should wave a תנופה. Tnufa.
That becomes—it use an abstract noun, a waving. So there's only one
waving. Okay? There's never an abstract noun that's used by סמיכה. Smicha.
Some say you should be סומך ידיו somech yadav and do a
סמיכה, Smicha, and that we could say סמיכה ולא סמיכות. smicha v'lo
smichot. No, you know, it's—it only is the verb. So therefore each
individual can do the act of
סמיכה. Smicha. ולא תנופות. V'lo tnufot. וסמיכה בשחוטין ליתא? U'smicha b'shechutin leita?
Now the גמרא—so Gemara fine. Now we understand why they have these
differences. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to question if this is
really
true. That the—is the assertion that סמיכה Smicha only applies by live
animals, is that actually correct? וסמיכה בשחוטין ליתא והתנן? U'smicha b'shechutin leita
v'hatnan? We taught in a משנה, Mishna, בזמן שכהן גדול רוצה להקטיר,
bizman she-kohen gadol rotzeh l'haktir, when a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would
always have the prerogative if he wants to go ahead and to,
you know, do the עבודה, avoda, he could walk and do the
עבודה. avoda. And if he wanted to burn the limbs of an
עולה, olah, you know, onto the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. So
בזמן שהוא
רוצה להקטיר—okay,
bizman she-hu
rotzeh l'haktir so—עולה בכבש, olah b'kevesh, he goes up on the ramp.
והסגן בימינו. V'hasgan biyemino. And the, you know, assistant—like the second to
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is there on his right hand. הגיע
למחצית הכבש, Higi'a l'machatzit hakevesh, he gets halfway up the ramp. אחז
סגן בימינו והעלהו. Achaz sgan biyemino v'he'alehu.
והושיט לו הראשון הראש
והרגל.
V'hoshit lo harishon
harosh v'haregel. So if—so the סגן Sgan would hold onto the right
hand of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and he would help him
get to the top of the ramp. So when it says he
would get to מחצית הכבש, machatzit hakevesh, presumably it means like maybe
he got tired when he got to half of the ramp. So
the סגן Sgan sort of like a whole—משה אהרן וחור—the Moshe, Aharon
v'Chur סגן Sgan would hold—help him and help bring him up to
the top of the ramp. That's presumably what that means. אחז סגן
בימינו והעלהו. Achaz sgan biyemino v'he'alehu. Could also maybe just mean that
that was a way of like respect, that he was walking up
with a retinue. But it sounds like the סגן Sgan needed to
assist him. והושיט לו הראשון הראש והרגל, V'hoshit lo harishon harosh v'haregel,
and, you know, he
would then
take—now not he, not the סגן, Sgan, the הראשון, harishon, the הראשון
harishon is the first כהן, Kohen, you know, the כהנים Kohanim would
be divided into
groups. the pieces of the קרבן Korban up to the מזבח Mizbeach
would stick out to the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the ראש והרגל,
rosh veharegel, the head of the קרבן Korban and the foot. סומך
עליהם, somech aleihem, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would put his hands
on them, ויזרקן, veyizrakan, and he would throw them onto the fire.
הושיט
השני לראשון, hoshit hasheni larishon, now the second כהן Kohen who was
bringing the next part of the קרבן Korban would hand his part
to the first כהן. Kohen. מה הוא מביא, mah hu mevi, what
would he be bringing? שתי ידיים, shtei yadayim, the two forelegs, ונתנו
לכהן גדול, unetano lekohen gadol, and then the first one would give
it to the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, so it would be
a whole like chain because this would just be seen like as
a whole production, which would make it a more sort of honored
thing that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is doing with all these
כהנים Kohanim that were involved. So the second gave it to the
first, וסומך עליהם, vesomech aleihem, and then the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
would put his hands on this part of the קרבן, Korban, the
forelegs, ויזרקן, veyizrakan, and put them on the מזבח. Mizbeach. נשמט השני
והלך לו, nishmat hasheni vehalach lo, the second כהן Kohen stepped away,
וכך היו מושיטין לו שאר כל האיברים. vechach hayu moshitin lo shear
kol haeivarim.
And then the third כהן Kohen would come, bring his part of
it, give it to the first, the first would give it to
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. סומך עליהם ויזרקן, somech aleihem veyizrakan, and
then the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would put his hands on it
and throw them on the מזבח. Mizbeach. ובזמן שהוא רוצה הוא סומך
ואחרים זורקין, uvizman shehu rotzeh hu somech veacherim zorkin, and if the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol wanted, he would do the סמיכה smicha and
let somebody else throw it on the fire. So anyway, this is
a whole production that they would do with the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol in order
to have him play this whole role of putting the portions of
the קרבן Korban on the fire. And what he would do is
he would do a סמיכה smicha on these portions of the קרבן.
Korban. So you see you're doing סמיכה smicha on something that's שחט.
shachted. So there's an obvious answer here, which is like there's absolutely
no basis for this in a Torah. It's obviously just part of
some type of procedure that they're doing to make a big production
out of it, and it's not a real סמיכה. smicha. So that's
what אביי Abaye says, אמר אביי התם משום כבודו דכהן גדול. amar
Abaye hatam mishum kevodo dekohen gadol. We're doing it to give honor
to the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. It does not really have any
הלכתי halachic significance. Okay, and with that we end the פרק: perek:
הדרן עלך שתי מידות. hadran alach shtei midot.
Now before we continue on to the next פרק, perek, I have
to share something with you about this whole procedure with the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol because the source of this, or a record that
reflects this reality, is quite ancient, and that is in the Wisdom
Book of בן סירא, Ben Sira, which is second century before the
Common Era. At the very end, chapter fifty, here's what you have.
And this will be recognizable to you not only in its description
of what we just read about the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, but
also from יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And here's what it says: גדול
אחיו ותפארת עמו שמעון בן יוחנן הכהן. gadol achiv vetiferet amo Shimon
ben Yochanan HaKohen. Shimon ben Yochanan the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was
great, the great one of his brothers, the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, glorious and so on. And then it says
a few verses
about him or about the period. And then it says here in
verse ה: hei: מה נהדר בהשקיפו מאהל ובצאתו מבית הפרוכת. mah nehedar
behashkifo me'ohel uvetzeito mibeit haparochet. How glorious was it when he visited
the tent and when he came out from the
קודש הקודשים: Kodesh Hakodashim: ככוכב אור מבין עבים וכירח מלא בימי מועד
כשמש מזהרת על היכל המלך וכקשת נראה בענן כנץ ענף בימי מועד
וכשושן על יבלי מים כפרח לבנון בימי קיץ וכאש לבונה מנחה,
kechochav or mibein avim ucheyareach male biyemei moed keshemesh mazheret al heichal
hamelech uchekeshet nira be'anan kenetz anaf biyemei moed
ucheshoshan al yivlei mayim keferach Levanon biyemei kayitz uche'esh levona mincha, etc.,
etc. So very much, I assume that that is evoking for you
מה נהדר מראה כהן גדול mah nehedar mareh Kohen Gadol when he
בצאתו מבית קודש הקודשים. betzeito mibeit Kodesh Hakodashim. So it's not the
exact same words that are used to describe, but it seems that
that פזמון, pizmon, that פזמון pizmon goes way, way back and is
sourced ultimately in this section of בן סירא, Ben Sira, and that
describes him coming out of the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. But then
it says the following. It says: בעלותו על מזבח הוד ויהדר עזרת
מקדש בקבלו נתחים מיד אחיו, be'aloto al mizbeach hod veyehedar ezrat mikdash
bekabelo netachim miyad achiv, when he would go up to the glorious
מזבח Mizbeach and would honor the courtyard of the sanctuary, receiving the
portions from the hands of his brothers, the other כהנים. Kohanim. והוא
ניצב על המערכות, vehu nitzav al hamaarachot, and he was standing there
by the fires. סביב לו עטרת בנים כשתילי ארזים בלבנון ויקיפוהו כערבי
נחל כל בני אהרן בכבודם. saviv lo ateret banim keshtilei arazim balevanon
veyakifuhu kearvei nachal kol benei Aharon bichvodam. All of the כהנים Kohanim
would be surrounding him, sort of like this whole thing we just
read of the production of the כהנים. Kohanim. ואשי השם בידם, ve'ishei
Hashem beyadam, God's fire offerings were in the hands of the כהנים,
Kohanim, נגד כל קהל ישראל עד כלות שרת המזבח, neged kol kehal
Yisrael ad kalot sheret hamizbeach, and they would all stand around until
he would finish to serve on the altar לסדר מערכות עליון. lesader
maarachot elyon. אז יריעו בני אהרן, az yari'u benei Aharon, and after
he finished, they would trumpet,
הכהנים בחצוצרות מקשה, hakohanim bachatzotzerot miksha, etc., etc. So very quite fascinating
that this is really all
recorded. and what's also quite fascinating is you know the focus on
the עבודה avoda of a כהן גדול kohen gadol would be putting
the things on the fire. Everything we've learned in זבחים Zevachim has
been how it's all about the blood. The burning of the קרבן
korban of the pieces of the קרבנות korbanot has seemed very secondary.
By מנחות Menachot fine, you burn the קטורת ketoret and the קומץ.
kometz. But by the animal קרבנות korbanot the focus is completely on
the blood. And here, that's not necessarily so clear from the פסוקים.
pesukim. Yes, the פסוקים pesukim say כי הדם על המזבח הוא יכפר,
ki hadam al hamizbe'ach hu yechaper, but in the description of the
קרבנות korbanot in the תורה, Torah, there's a lot of emphasis about
אשי ריח ניחוח ishei rei'ach nicho'ach and about the fire offering and
about raising you know putting it on the altar and it burning
up and that interestingly is the one thing that is really focused
on here with the עבודה avoda of the כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
Okay and with that we end this פרק perek הדרן עלך שתי
מידות. hadran alach shtei midot. And we begin now the next פרק.
perek. And we get back at least briefly to מנחות Menachot before
we get onto another topic once again. שתי הלחם נילושות אחת אחת
ונאפות אחת אחת. shtei halechem niloshot achat achat vene'afot achat achat. Okay
when you deal with the שתי הלחם shtei halechem of שבועות, Shavuot,
they each one is you know
kneaded K-N-E-A-D kneaded, they're kneaded individually and they are baked individually. לחם
הפנים lechem hapanim
when you get to the 12 loaves of לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim,
נילושות אחת אחת ונאפות שתים שתים. niloshot achat achat vene'afot shtayim shtayim.
Each individual bread is kneaded separately but they are baked to you
know in twos. All right, שתים שתים. shtayim shtayim. ובדפוס היה עושהן
uvidfus haya osan
and they would be baked in a form, in like a mold,
because as we'll see they had to have a very particular shape
and you need the mold in order to hold the shape. And
in order to you know you can make the shape by the
dough but you want it to bake accordingly so you have a
mold. וכשרודן ukisherodan
and when you peel them off the wall of the oven because
that's how they made bread they would sort of stick it to
the wall of the oven, נותנן לדפוס כדי שלא יתקלקל. notnan lidfus
kedei shelo yitkalkel. You would also put them in a in another
mold to help so that they would not crumble and they would
also retain their shape after they were removed. People have like baked
cakes and like bundt cakes and the whole type of thing understand
how important that is to have it in a mold when it's
baking and then you know you want it to retain the shape
afterwards as well. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? Where do you get this from
that there are you know kneaded and baked separately or in twos?
דתנו רבנן. detanu rabanan. We taught: שני עשרונים יהיה החלה האחת. shnei
esronim yihye hachala ha'achat. That is by the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim.
So 12 loaves and each one is two עשרונים. esronim. That is
quite large right if you think about it like a מנחה mincha
is normally just one עיסרון isaron and sometimes when you make these
loaves like by the תודה todah it's like one עיסרון isaron for
like ten loaves. Here it is two עשרונים esronim for just one
loaf of the of the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. מלמד שנילושה אחת
אחת. melamed shenilosha achat achat.
So because it says החלה האחת, hachala ha'achat, you deal it each
one is separate individual so they are kneaded separately. מנין לשתי הלחם
כך? minal lishtei halechem kach? How do you know by the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem also each one is kneaded separately? תלמוד לומר יהיה.
talmud lomar yihye.
So the extra יהיה yihye is coming to tell me I don't
know what else it could have said but also by another חלה
chala it also each one is individual. ומנין שאפייתן שתים שתים? uminayin
she'afiyatan shtayim shtayim?
How do you know by the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim that you
bake them two at a time? תלמוד לומר ושמת אותם. talmud lomar
vesamta otam.
You shall place them. So that's where they are being you know
grouped together. יכול אף שתי הלחם כן? yachol af shtei halechem ken?
Not exactly by the way clear to
me first of all that simple פשט pshat is that it's putting
it on the שולחן shulchan but also how do you exactly know
that the "them" means two? Maybe it means more than two. So
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, ושמת אותם. vesamta otam. רש"י Rashi
says שימה ראשונה שאתה עושה מהן דהיינו בתנור. sima rishona she'ata ose
mehen dehainu batanur. The first placing you do with them which is
the placing in the oven. Okay. So
נותן שתים בשני דפוסים יחד בתנור. noten shtayim bishnei dfusim yachad batanur.
So it should be in an אותם otam and I guess the
דרשה drasha is the minimum אותם otam is two. All right so
place them, the placing in the תנור tanur is two at a
time. יכול אף שתי הלחם כן? yachol af shtei halechem ken? Maybe
the same should be for the שתי הלחם? shtei halechem? תלמוד לומר
אותם. talmud lomar otam. Them meaning only them. So the גמרא Gemara
says האי אותם האי אפיקתיה. hai otam hai afiktei. How can you
you already used the אותם otam to tell me that you're doing
it two at a time? How can you use it to say
only this by the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and not by the
שתי הלחם? shtei halechem? So the גמרא Gemara says no, אם כן
לימא קרא ושמתם. im ken leima kra vesamtam. It could have just
said "place them" without a separate word of אותם otam and that
would have already used the plural and told you two at a
time. מאי ושמת אותם? mai vesamta otam? Why did it make the
word a separate word אותם? otam? שמע מינה תרתי. shma mina tarti.
To tell you the placing is two at a time a minimum
of אותם otam and only them and not by the שתי הלחם.
shtei halechem. and not the and not the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem.
Okay, so that's the basic point of the משנה, mishna, what the
פסוקים psukim are that it is based on. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan
וסמת אותם vesamta otam בדפוס bedfus you shall place them in a
mold. All right, and it's not like getting it necessarily from the
פסוק pasuk but just that's a reality if you want to bake
them in a certain shape, you know, you need to put a
mold in it. Could be maybe it's also learning the same way
it understood וסמת vesamta means put in an oven, maybe here it's
reading that the word שימה sima means in a mold, but maybe
it's just a reality. שלשה דפוסים הן sheloshah defusim hein there were
three molds that they had.
נותנה לדפוס ועדיין היא בצק nosna ladfus vadayin hi batzeik first of
all when it was still dough you would put it in the
mold so that it could,
you know, as you're forming it, you want to form it according
to a certain shape, so you use the mold to form it.
Then וכמין דפוס היה לה בתנור uchmin defus hayeh la batanur and
then you move it to the oven and there's a mold in
the oven, maybe the first one wasn't oven safe, whatever the reason
is that you needed a separate one in the oven, and you
have a mold so then when it's baking in the oven it's
keeping to that shape. וכשהוא רודה נותנה בדפוס uchshehu rodeh nosna badfus
and when you take it out of the oven, you put it
in another mold to help it retain the shape
כדי שלא תתקלקל kedei shelo titkalkel in order that it should not
get ruined. So the גמרא Gemara says להדא לדפוס קמא lahadu ladfus
kama so why, fine, maybe you needed,
you know, a different type of a metal, like you know maybe
you have a precious metal when it's outside the oven, you have
something like iron inside the oven, so we get why you need
a different type
of a mold in the oven, but when it came out of
the oven why didn't you put it back in the first mold?
And the answer's pretty obvious כיון דאפיה נפה keivan de'aphilei nafcha no,
because once it baked it expanded, so it's not going to fit
in the first mold. You need a bigger mold, you still want
it to retain the shape, but it has now expanded so you
need a different mold. Okay, איתמר itmar it was taught לחם הפנים
כיצד עושין אותה lechem panim keitzad osin oso how would they make
לחם הפנים? lechem panim?
What did it look like? Top of צדי דלד עמוד ב tzaddi
daled amud bet רבי חנינא אמר Rabbi Chanina amar רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina says כמין תיבה פרוצה kemin teiva prutza it would be like
an open box. If you look at רשי, Rashi, you know, it's
basically and I assume people have seen various diagrams or you know
drawings of reconstructing what it would look like basically based on this
גמרא. Gemara. So you would basically have like a flat sheet and
then you would raise up the edges and so you would basically
have an open box, okay, nothing on, you know, walls on two
sides, nothing on the other, nothing on the top.
רבי יוחנן אמר כמין ספינה רוקדת Rabbi Yochanan amar kemin sefina rokedes
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
like a shaking boat or like a boat that like רשי Rashi
says is like a racing boat, it comes to a V and
it can go through the water very quickly. So you see here
the picture in רשי, Rashi, right, very like a V. תוספות Tosafot
however has it that this is does not mean to reject
the idea that the walls would go up direct at 90 angle
90 degree angles. If you take a look at תוספות Tosafot the
second picture, ignore the bottom part of it, but it would be
a V and then at the tops of the edges of the
V would go up as straight walls. Okay, but we'll just work
with רשי. Rashi. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this בשלמא
למאן דאמר כמין תיבה פרוצה bishlama leman d'amar kemin teiva prutza
it works according to the one that says it's an open box
היינו דהוו
יתבי בזיכין hainu dehavu yasvi b'zichin so then we get where the
you know where the little spoons of the frankincense would sit because
the תורה Torah says you should put these two spoons of frankincense
you should put it על המערכות al hamarchot on the columns of
the bread, which the גמרא Gemara understands to mean on the top
bread of each of the you know of each of the columns.
So if you've got a flat base in the bread, you can
put the little cup of you know the little dish of frankincense
in that flat base so that makes sense היינו דהוו יתבי בזיכין.
hainu dehavu yasvi b'zichin. אלא למאן דאמר כמין ספינה רוקדת ela leman
d'amar kemin sefina rokedes but if it's like a racing boat, if
it comes to a bottom of a V היכי הוו יתבי בזיכין
heichi havu yasvi b'zichin where would you put the you know these
the little dishes of the frankincense in the bread? So the גמרא
Gemara says מקום עביד לה makom avid leh all right, you would
make a place in it, like רשי Rashi says maybe you'd like
flatten out something or make a niche in one of the walls
and you'd insert it into that niche. You'd you know you'd do
something to adjust the bread so that it could settle. Okay, you
could also you know just have if have the base of it
go down so that the two walls on the two side of
the V when it gets towards the bottom you know are sort
of supporting it that way it's like suspending itself from the two
opposite edges. Anyway you'd make it work.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues so בשלמא למאן דאמר כמין
תיבה פרוצה היינו. bishlama leman d'amar kemin teiva prutza hainu. So if
you say it's like an open box, היינו דהוי יתבי קני hainu
dehavi yasve kani so that's where we understand where the pegs would
sit. What does this mean the pegs? So if you look at
the picture down at רש"י Rashi you sort of see sort of
think about like a bookcase. You've got the two panels on the
side and then you've got pegs going out and the pegs or
here I should say rods they would go from end to end
presumably from one panel to the next. And then we put a
shelf on the pegs they would put the bread on the pegs.
Okay fine. But how do we put those pegs in because we
have like holes in the panel and that's but the גמרא Gemara
here assumes that these rods that would go from one panel to
the next would sort of sit on the top of the bread
and be supported by the bread. So the rods that would separate
one bread from the next would be sitting and resting on the
top of the bread below it. So the גמרא Gemara says well
if you've got it like an open box then you've got like
thick walls the walls have a certain thickness those perpendicular walls and
the rods can rest on the thickness of those walls at the
top edge of those walls. But if it's coming as a V
so then it's sort of narrowing the thickness of the wall and
it's certainly at an angle but רש"י Rashi also understands that the
thickness is narrowing. So how are the rods being supported by the
edges of the wall of the bottom חלה? challah? So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא למאן דאמר כספינה רוקדת קני
היכי הוו יתבי?
Ella leman deamar kesafina rokedes kani haychi
havi yasvi?
Where would the rods sit? מושא עביד להו Mosha avid lehu so
רש"י Rashi basically says like you would make use a little dough
to stick it to the edge of the to the top of
the bread underneath.
So they would make like a protrusion so even though the top
of the walls were narrowing as they were getting to the top
of the V but they would also flatten it out a little
bit דוקא davka in order
to support the rods that would rest on top of it. Okay.
בשלמא למאן דאמר כתיבה פרוצה היינו דסמכי לסניפין ולחם. Bishlama leman deamar
keteiva perutza hainu desamchei lesniffin ulacham.
If you say it is like an open box so you understand
how the סניפין sniffin those are like the panels help support the
bread right because support here doesn't mean support their weight from underneath
but it means keeps them in place you also don't want them
moving back and forth so they're supporting them vertically they're supporting the
sides so that makes sense. אלא למאן דאמר כספינה רוקדת Ella leman
deamar kesafina rokedes
but if it is like a rocking or like a racing ship
היכי סמכי לסניפין ולחם? haychi samchei lesniffin ulacham?
How did the panels help support the bread keep it in place?
I mean again you've got this like V thing
going a bigger question would not just be how do the panels
support it but how does the bread stay upright? If it's a
V then it's just resting on like a point below on the
bars of the bread below it so how is that not tipping
over?
So maybe a similar question. So the גמרא Gemara says דעגלי מעגלי
deagelei meagelei because you would actually like curve it round it about.
So if you take a look at again the bottom left picture
on רש"י Rashi so if the bars would sort of be also
coming in a V shape then the bars would actually would actually
support the bread above it.
Okay. בשלמא למאן דאמר כספינה רוקדת היינו דבעינן סניפין. Bishlama leman deamar
kesafina rokedes hainu devinan sniffin.
If you say that it is like a finally one thing works
better if it's based like a ship if it's like a racing
ship you understand
why you need the panels all together right? Because without the panels
as we just said how is the whole thing going to be
supported? It all comes to a point the whole thing would collapse.
You need the whole contraption of the panels to keep the
thing to keep the thing supported. אלא למאן דאמר כתיבה פרוצה ella
leman deamar keteiva perutza
but if it's like an open box סניפין למה לי? sniffin lamah
li? Why do you even need the panels? Why don't you just
stack them one on top of the other and they can just
be free on the top of the table? Who needs this whole
contraption? So the גמרא Gemara says no אגב יוקרא דלחמא חלץ agav
yukra delachma chals
because of the weight of the
bread it would break the bread beneath it so you need the
panels and you need the rods to help separate one bread from
the other not to support it. Support it you could just stack
them but you need the contraption of the panels and the rods
to help let air go through them to help them not the
weight not weigh down. But yes for the boat shape you need
the whole contraption just to keep
everything supported.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא למאן דאמר
כמין ספינה רוקדת,
Bishlama leman de'amar kemin
sefina rokedet,
it works if it's like a boat. סניפין על גבי שלחן מונחים.
Snifin algabei shulchan munachim. So then the actual panels could start at
the base of the table. Why? Because at the very base of
the table, the bread only comes to a point. So there's actually
space at the base of the table, and you could build up
the panels starting from the surface of the table. Okay, and also
when it gets to the top of the V, רש"י Rashi says
it comes to a narrow point. So you've got the space and
you could actually build the panels on the table itself. אלא למאן
דאמר כמין תיבה פרוצה, Ela leman de'amar kemin teiva perutza, but if
it's like this open box, so סניפין היכי מנח להו? snifin heichi
manach lehu? Where do you put the panels? Because the box goes
from one edge of the table to the other edge,
and there's not any room for the panels themselves. Okay, so if
we understand that the width of the bread is the width of
the table, so in the V shape you only get to that
width at the top and it's anyway narrowed there. So again, there's
place to put the panels on the surface of the table itself.
But if it's a box, the width totally fills the table at
the bottom. So how do you build out the panels? So the
גמרא Gemara says,
so it says אארעא, a'ara, so you put them on the ground.
That they are built out
starting from the ground like the pictures show you, and they come
up on the outside edge of the table and they're not built
on the inside of the table.
All right. אארעא מנח להו. A'ara manach lehu. So, I'm sorry, I
misread that. So היכי מנח להו? אארעא מנח להו? Heichi manach lehu?
A'ara manach lehu? Where would they put the panels? Would they put
them on the ground? So the גמרא Gemara says אין, in, yes,
they would put them on the ground. דאמר רבי אבא בר ממל,
De'amar Rabbi Abba bar Memel, לדברי אומר כמין ספינה רוקדת, lidivrei omer
kemin sefina rokedet, according to the one that says it's like a
racing boat, סניפין על גבי שלחן מונחים. snifin algabei shulchan munachim. You
would build out the panels from the surface of the table. לדברי
אומר כמין תיבה פרוצה, lidivrei omer kemin teiva perutza, and if you
say that it is like an open box, סניפין על גבי קרקע
מונחים. snifin algabei karka munachim. You would build them out from the
ground and they would come up on the edge of the table.
כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רבי יהודה, Keman azla ha de'amar Rabbi Yehuda,
how does it go that which says רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, הלחם
מעמיד את הסניפין והסניפין
מעמידים את הלחם?
halechem ma'amid et hasnifin vehasnifin
ma'amidin et halechem? The bread supports the panels and the panels support
the bread. It doesn't literally mean the bread supports the panels, but
sort of like they are pushing up against one another, they're like
tension is holding one another. כמאן
דאמר כמין ספינה רוקדת. Keman de'amar kemin sefina rokedet. So like the
approach that it is like a boat. Why? So רש"י Rashi says
what this means is that if it's at an angle, because you
have the bars that are coming from the panels that are supporting
it, so that is somehow considered that the bread is supporting the
panels. I don't exactly fully understand that. רש"י Rashi says the panels
support the bread that it doesn't fall, but somehow the pressure of
the bread on those bent bars is pushing against the panels. I
don't fully understand that, but somehow if it is the idea of
the flat box, then yes, the weight of the bread is on
the panels, but the bread is somehow on the bars, but somehow
the bread is not pushing up against the panels in the same
way. I must tell you I don't really fully understand that. Okay,
this is a good place to stop.